A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Carl TenBroeck papers FA968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Carl TenBroeck papers
1914-1951
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. Department of Plant Pathology
FA968
0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box.
1 box and 1 volume.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Carl TenBroeck, 1885-1966, physician and researcher in animal pathology, Director of the Princeton laboratories of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research 1930-1950, worked with hog cholera virus and bacilli of the paratyphoid group, with the tetanus bacillus and on the problem of the transmission of encephalitis. He was an important influence in animal pathology in changing the emphasis from comparative pathology to virology.
Married to Janet Rinaker April 28, 1917
Children: Carlon (deceased 1928); Jane, Nancy
In 1966 daughter Jane was married (Mrs. Frank Gay) and living in Wilmington, Del.
Biographical / Historical
Member of American Academy of Arts and Sciences, American Society of Immunologists, Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine
Scope and Contents
Consists primarily of administrative correspondence with Business Manager while Director of the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology in Princeton.
File Plan
Former Classification: I 425-6
Related Materials
See RU card catalog for further correspondence with Carl TenBroeck and dealing with the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of Carl TenBroeck were deposited with the Rockefeller University archives by the Business Manager.
Other Finding Aids
FA834 Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Correspondence.
FA835 Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Subject Files.
FA969 Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Publications.
Diseases; Biochemistry; Medical technology; Plant diseases; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Animals -- Diseases; Medical sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Technology; Life sciences; Medical education; Medical research; Biology -- Research; Pathology
- Carl TenBroeck papers, 1914-1951
  Biographical/Historical note
  Biographical note
  1885 Born September 5, Parsons, Kansas
  1908 A.B. University of Illinois
  1913 M.D. Harvard University Medical School
  1914-1915 Assistant, Animal Pathology, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, Princeton
  1915-1920 Associate, Animal Pathology, RIMR, Princeton
  1917-1918 1st Lieutenant, U.S. Army Medical Corps
  1920-1923 Associate Professor, bacteriology, Peking Union Medical College, Peking, China
  1923-1927 Professor and Department Chief in bacteriology, PUMC
  1927-1928 Member, Animal Pathology, RIMR, Princeton
  1929-1930 Member, Acting Director, Animal Pathology, RIMR, Princeton
  1930-1951 Member, Director, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, RIMR, Princeton
  1943-1944 Consultant to U.S. Secretary of War
  1951-1966 Member Emeritus RIMR
  1966 Died November 4 at Bar Harbor, Maine
  1943-1944 Director of a special commission on Dysentery in Hawaii and in the India-Burma Theatre for the Secretary of War, U.S.
  1946 (April) Receives The U.S. Medal of Freedom for this service under the Army Epidemiological Board.
  - 1943-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Biographical summary and photocopy of Rockefeller University review, September/October 1966 pp. 20-21.
    1942/1944 Descriptive pamphlet summary of Department of Animal and Plant Pathology 1943 Scientific report mimeographed copy.
    Photographs.
    Bibliography.
  - Correspondence, 1913-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Primarily administrative correspondence with Henry James, business manager, but also included early letters on joining the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. Some letters while on leave October 1918-May 1919 with the U.S. Army as a Lieutenant. Also includes his resignation in 1920. Many letters are handwritten. The administrative correspondence deals with the establishment of procedures for the new department in Princeton.
  - Correspondence from Peking Union Medical College and with his acceptance of offer of appointment as Member of RIMR, 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letters deal with arrangements for his return, and to bring some experimental mice to the United States. June 1927-June 1928 was spent abroad (Europe) and a letter from Abraham Flexner asks him to make some studies for him of the conditions in Europe for the study of animal pathology. A handwritten note from Edric Smith Nov. 12, 1928 deals with the death of TenBroeck's son.
  - Administrative correspondence
    - 1928 December-1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Deals with appointments, salaries, equipment purchase, personnel and travel to conferences.
      16 June 1929 is appointed Acting Director of the Dept. and September 30 as Director for 4 years, making a 5-year appointment.
    - 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Some handwritten letters and also handwritten copies of Flexner letters from which typed copies are made.
    - 1935-1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      In 1934 Simon Flexner retired and Herbert Gasser became Director of the RIMR laboratories.
    - untitled (Box 1, Folder 7)
      After 1951 Dr. TenBroeck's address is Jackson Memorial Laboratory, Bar Harbor, Maine.
  - Collected reprints
    Separated Materials
    Relocated to the RAC Library, 8/9/88.